<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for, and an invitation to the people call'd Quakers to rectifie some errors which through the scandals givers they have fallen into : wherein the true original causes both humane and divine of all the divisions of the church and mischiefs in the state and among the people are plainly and briefly opened and detected.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07869758</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07869758</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1213:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for, and an invitation to the people call'd Quakers to rectifie some errors which through the scandals givers they have fallen into : wherein the true original causes both humane and divine of all the divisions of the church and mischiefs in the state and among the people are plainly and briefly opened and detected.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens [who wrote under the name of Socrates Christianus]--National union catalog pre-l956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40207:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40207:1"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY For, and an INVITATION To, the PEOPLE call'd QUAKERS, TO Rectifie ſome ERRORS, which through the <hi>Scandals</hi> given they have fallen into.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The true Original Cauſes, both Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Divine, of all the <hi>Diviſions</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and among the <hi>People,</hi> are plainly and briefly opened and detected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:40207:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40207:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THAT whole Bodies or Societies of Men are ſubject to the ſame Infirmities, which the Individuals, of which they conſiſt, are, and often Sick of the ſame Diſeaſes, and the very worſt of all, thoſe of the Mind, <hi>Blindneſs, Conceitedneſs, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs, Obſtinacy, Incorrigibleneſs,</hi> and <hi>Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> of <hi>Reproof,</hi> or even <hi>Friendly Admonition,</hi> the Experience of all Ages doth abundantly manifeſt; but in none is it more manifeſt, than in the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom God raiſed up to be an <hi>Example, Admonition,</hi> and <hi>Warning,</hi> to the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. Their whole <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and all their <hi>Prophets,</hi> are Teſtimonies of this all along from firſt to laſt; and of this height of the Diſeaſe to be moſt offended and inraged againſt their beſt Friends, ſuch as moſt earneſtly deſire, and moſt faithfully ſeek and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Good and Recovery; They reckon them their Enemies, who tell them the Truth, <hi>Iſa. 29.21. make a Man an Offender for a Word, and lay a Snare for him, who Reproveth in the Gate,</hi> that is, publickly, for National Sins, and thoſe of the Great Ones. Act. <hi>7.52. Which of the Prophets
<pb facs="tcp:40207:3"/>have not your Fathers Perſecuted?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Stephen.</hi> Beſides this common Infirmity, it is very obſeravble, in the unhappy Diviſions which are now among Chriſtians, that generally in all, there is a greater Zeal and concern for their own Church or Party, than for the common Intereſt of Chriſtianity, and the real Service of God, and Salvation of Souls. And this being ſo, What Entertainment is ſuch a Diſcourſe as this like to meet with in the World? But if it be conſidered for what End, and for whoſe Service it is written, that may be ſufficient for Encouragement to the <hi>Author,</hi> and for Caution to the <hi>Reader,</hi> how he treats it. And that, with the Leſſon now to be read, <hi>(Decemb. 18.)</hi> may ſerve for ſufficient Advertiſement, <hi>Iſa. 50.7, 8, 9. The Lord God will help me, therefore ſhall I not be confounded: therefore have I ſet my Face like a Flint, and I know that I ſhall not be aſhamed. He is near that juſtifieth me, Who will contend with me? let us ſtand together: Who is mine Adverſary? let him come near to me. Behold the Lord God will help me, Who is he that ſhall condemn me? lo, they all ſhall wax old as a Garment: the Moth ſhall eat them up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some things but briefly mentioned here upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which may ſeem doubtful or obſcure, are intended, upon another more proper, to be more fully explained and cleared.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40207:3"/>
            <head>An Apology for, And an Invitation to, The PEOPLE call'd QUAKERS, To rectifie ſome ERRORS, which through the <hi>Scandals</hi> given, they have fallen into, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALmighty <hi>God</hi> doth in many things <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi> the greater Collective Bodies of <hi>Men,</hi> as he doth the leſſer of Families, and ſingle Perſons: and therefore what is the <hi>Duty</hi> of ſingle Perſons, or of the Heads of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, under ſeveral occurrences of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, the very ſame is the <hi>Duty</hi> of the Governors of thoſe greater Bodies, whether they be Civil, or Eccleſiaſtical. And therefore again, as when any Croſs or Affliction befalls a Perſon, if he have any Senſe of God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40207:4"/>in him, he ought not to neglect it, as an inſenſible Creature, or a brute Beaſt; nor to look upon it, as a meer Accident and Misfortune, like an Atheiſt or Infidel; but to acknowledge the Hand and Providence of God in it, examin himſelf, and conſider well for what intent or purpoſe, it may have been ordered or permitted by the Righteous, Wiſe, and Gracious Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Providence of God, and without delay apply himſelf to do and perform what that Diſpenſation doth appear to him to call for.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Diviſions, Schiſms, and Separations</hi> of Parties do fall out in a Church, theſe are ſuch Afflictions, as ought to be looked upon, as the Loſs of one in a Family, or of a Member in a particular Perſon; and therefore not to be made light of, or paſſed over as Misfortunes and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, but to be well conſidered, as ordered or permitted by the Special Providence of God, with great Juſtice and Wiſdom, and therefore for ſome ſpecial End to be inquired into, taken notice of, and obſerved by his Church, that they may thereupon apply themſelves to what he requireth of them for his Service and their own Good. When this is neglected, all other Means uſually prove not only ineffectual, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of more or greater Evils.</p>
            <p>What was written afore-time, was written for our Admonition and Inſtruction: and as we are plainly told, that in the Diviſion and Separation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40207:4"/>of the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> from the Houſe of <hi>David, the Cauſe was from the Lord,</hi> 1 Ki. 12.15. So in that great <hi>Diviſion of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches,</hi> and breach of Communion between them; and in the Weſtern Church that great Diviſion and <hi>Separation of all thoſe Churches, call'd Reform'd;</hi> and in the great Diviſion again amongſt them into <hi>Lutheran and Calvanist,</hi> and the ſeveral <hi>Sub-diviſions</hi> of ſeveral Parties and Sects amongſt them; and laſtly, to come nearer home, in all the Diviſions, Sub-diviſions, Sects and Parties, which have ſeparated from <hi>the Church of England,</hi> and afterward one from another, there is as certainly the Hand of God, and did we conſider it well, we might plainly ſee that the Cauſe is from the Lord.</p>
            <p>This we can all ſee in the Great Diviſion, and Separation of all theſe Churches call'd <hi>Reformed,</hi> from that of <hi>Rome;</hi> but ſhe her ſelf either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not or will not ſee it: And this, to ſay no more of the Foreigners here, our Diſſenters at home think they ſee, and do ſee; but we of the <hi>Church of England</hi> do not ſee, or will not ſee, to any purpoſe as we ought. But as they of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> lay all upon the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and will acknowledge nothing amiſs among themſelves; ſo we of the <hi>Church of England</hi> lay all upon the <hi>Separatiſts</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> but will acknowledge nothing amiſs among our ſelves. And that which dazzles the Eyes, and blinds the Minds of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40207:5"/>in both, is chiefly the Pomps and Vanities of the World (which are renounced at <hi>Baptiſm</hi>) without, and the God of this World, who blinds their Minds, within. The things of this World, to Earthly-minded People, are like Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-Plumbs to Children, which ſtop their Mouths, and ſatisfie them that all is well with them.</p>
            <p>But if things were more narrowly looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, it might be perceived, That there is ſcarce any Party of Separatiſts or Diſſenters, that hath not ſomething of <hi>Truth peculiar</hi> to them; and that there is ſomething in particular <hi>amiſs</hi> in the Church, which gave <hi>Occaſion</hi> to that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and whereof ſomething peculiar in that Sect may ſerve for Admonition. And therefore, that in all there is a ſecret <hi>Providence of God,</hi> ordering or permitting them for Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Correction, Reproof, and Admonition to reform, unto the Church, and unto thoſe very Parties, in which any ſuch Diviſion and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath been made. But generally all they, who ſhould have taken the Admonition, have had their Mouths ſo ſtopp'd, and been ſo bribed and enchanted with the Devil's Sugar-Plumbs and Baits of Preferments, that while all was ſo well with them, as they thought, they could ſee nothing amiſs in the Church, but magnified it, as a moſt glorious Church, and layed all the Fault upon the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> and <hi>Soparatiſts,</hi> who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40207:5"/>they thought only wanted what they were poſſeſſed of; and the Scandal of their Ambition, Pride and Covetouſneſs, and Neglect of a due Care of Souls, hath, by their Preaching, I doubt, betrayed more Souls into the Snares of the Devil, than all their Preaching hath reſcued out of them, and throughly converted unto God. It is <hi>a ſad Truth,</hi> but Truth it is, and a Great one too, and very manifeſt to all, whoſe Eyes are open, That our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> and Church <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments,</hi> which were deſigned by our Pious Anceſtors, for the promotion of true Piety, as well as Learning, are, by the Subtilty of Satan, and Neglect of true Piety and Devotion to God, become very ſubſervient to the Kingdom of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, leſs to the Kingdom of Light: From which corrupt <hi>Fountain</hi> hath proceeded, one way or other, not only all our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> but moſt of all the <hi>Evils,</hi> which do now afflict either the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical or Civil State: and if ſome very good Care be not ſpeedily taken, more and greater yet are more like to enſue, than theſe be removed.</p>
            <p>Of all the Sects which have ſprung up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, there is none more conſiderable in this reſpect, whereof I am ſpeaking, or leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as it ought to be, than that of the QUAKERS, as they are abuſively called; begun by <hi>GEORGE FOX,</hi> a young Man, born of mean, but honeſt and religious Parents, at <hi>Drayton</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> in the Year
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40207:6"/>of our Lord 1624. and educated from his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der years in the Fear of the Lord, but to no more Humane Learning than only to read <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> and write indifferently. He was in his Youth diſpoſed to Virtue and Piety; and when upward of Nineteen <hi>retired</hi> from his Relations and Acquaintance, and <hi>lived</hi> in divers places, <hi>where he was not known,</hi> working at his Trade of a <hi>Shoe-maker,</hi> with his hands for his Livelyhood, but exerciſing his Mind in ſerious Meditations, both while at his Work, and at other times of Leiſure eſpecially. In the Year 1646. he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, That <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity Learning</hi> was not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to qualifie Men to be Miniſters of Chriſt; and thereupon, inſtead of hearing them, uſed to <hi>retire</hi> with his Bible <hi>into Solitary places,</hi> joyning neither with the Miniſters of the Church, nor with the Diſſenters, but relying wholly upon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for his Inward Teaching. At another time he underſtood, That God, who made the World, did not dwell in Temples made with Hands, but in his Peoples Hearts. And in the Year 1647. having been for ſome time exerciſed with Temptations and Troubles in his Mind, he came farther to underſtand, <hi>That all was done, and to be done, in and by Christ;</hi> and, <hi>How he conquers and deſtroys the Tempter.</hi> And ſome time after he went among the Profeſſors at <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and <hi>declared Truth</hi> (as he calls it) amongſt them, and alſo at <hi>Broughton</hi> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40207:6"/>
               <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> and <hi>Mansfield</hi> in <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire;</hi> and then People came far and near to ſee him. And here his Preaching ſeems to have commenced. And in 1648. were divers Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Friends in ſeveral Places. And this was the Beginning of that Sect, which is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo conſiderable in outward Appearance, and I wiſh more conſiderable in a true inward Power than it is. For as all Man-kind are apt to relapſe and ſink down again from the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to which God at any time raiſed them: ſo I doubt are this People now relapſed very much into a Form, only of a different ſort and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</p>
            <p>The Beginning of <hi>George Fox</hi> ſeems to have been by and under a true Divine Conduct; ſuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> was led by; ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> was driven by from the Court of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> into the Wilderneſs; and ſuch as the Holy Prophets of Old, and greater numbers of Holy Chriſtians afterwards, were partly led, and partly driven by into the Wilderneſs, Solitary places, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement from Relations, Friends and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; as our Saviour ſaith, to forſake Father and Mother, Brother and Siſter, and Houſe and Land, for his ſake: and in thoſe Retirements he did receive <hi>Openings,</hi> as he calls it, of Truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: and when he came from his Retirement, and went into the Meetings of Profeſſors, he did <hi>declare Truth</hi> indeed, as he expreſſeth it. For
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40207:7"/>it is a certain Truth, that Univerſity Learning, that Preaching and Praying at Churches, or elſewhere, that the Studying of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that the Profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt, the Uſe of the Sacraments, and moſt frequent and conſtant uſe of the great and chief Solemnity of the Chriſtian Worſhip; nay, even Zeal for Chriſt, and doing Miracles in his Name, and Reliance upon his Merits, are all, though good in their kind, and very neceſſary, and ſome ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary; yet are all ſhort and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to thoſe, who reſt in them, and ſeek not in all and above all, that inward Principle of Light and Life, which is Chriſt in them, who receive him in Sincerity and Purity, and retain it by faithful and ready Obedience to his Conduct.</p>
            <p>This <hi>George</hi> ſaw very well and rightly. And if he did, in the heat of Diſputes, either through Tranſport, or any humane Infirmity, or through the Subtilty of Satan getting any Advantage of him, over-ſhoot himſelf, it is no more than what <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and the reſt of the Reformers, have done; who, whether they have reformed or deformed moſt, may very well bear a Diſpute; and he and his Party deſerve to be pitied, and helped out by gentle and kind means. And great <hi>reaſon</hi> there is <hi>for it,</hi> upon two accounts at the leaſt. 1. Becauſe the Scandals given were the occaſions of their Errors. 2. Becauſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity having before been pull'd to pieces, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40207:7"/>no where compleat, intire, and clear from Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and Abuſes to be found in any Church or Party of People in the World, they of all the parts choſe the better, the Soul, leaving the Body, as a dead Carcaſs to the reſt.</p>
            <p>It is true, this is in a great Meaſure to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to thoſe, who by their Empty Formality gave the Occaſion; yet it was a Fault in Them, who took ſuch Offence at it. What God hath joyned together, Man muſt not preſume to put aſunder: If the <hi>Leaper</hi> be commanded to waſh in <hi>Jordan,</hi> (2 King. 5.10.) he muſt not think that to waſh in the Rivers of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> will do as well: If the <hi>Blind Man</hi> be commanded to waſh in <hi>Siloam,</hi> (Jo. 9.7.) or even <hi>Moſes</hi> to caſt up Aſhes into the Air, (<hi>Exod.</hi> 9.8.) the Command muſt be obeyed and obſerved, or the Effect ſhall not follow: If People be command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Baptized in the Name of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> that their Sins may be forgiven, and that they may receive the Holy Ghoſt, (<hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 41.) if they preſume to neglect and cavil at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, their Sins are more like to be increaſed and faſter bound, than forgiven, and they more like to receive Satan transformed in a Spirit of Deluſion, than the Holy Spirit of God; and to die in their Sins, though with many falſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, than to come to true Reſt in the Lord, in any other way than he hath preſcribed. God's Command, if it be but the forbearing of an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40207:8"/>(<hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17: 3.3, 6, 11.) or the doing that, which our Reaſon cannot underſtand, muſt be obſerved punctually. Diſobedience to the Wiſdom of God, is no leſs a Sin than Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to his Will. And therefore I dare not excuſe this People in this; for their Sin may be greater, and their Caſe more dangerous, than they or I can imagin: but I cannot but pity them, be ready to help them, to hope the beſt, becauſe they were led into it, and did it through Ignorance, Prejudice, and the Scandals of others; and to ſpeak comfortably to all that will receive it, and ſubmit to <hi>the Call of God,</hi> humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before Him, and return to their Duty. But the Sin of thoſe, who ſhall refuſe, and go on obſtinately, will be greatly aggravated, and their Caſe more dangerous and difficult. If they fall into the Ditch, the company of a blind Guide will not ſave them: If they die in their Sins, it will be but a ſorry Comfort to them that their Blood muſt be required of another.</p>
            <p>But to help them out, I know no better and more effectual way, than to detect the Snare and Stratagem whereby they fell, and the Stone at which they ſtumbled. And it was no other than what I have mentioned already in general, the <hi>Scandal</hi> given by others, and <hi>Offence</hi> taken by them: but it will be neceſſary to conſider it more particularly: and the firſt particular, that I obſerve in the Journal of <hi>G. Fox,</hi> was an empty
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40207:8"/>
               <hi>Formality void of the Power</hi> of Godlineſs, that he perceived and felt in all Parties, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors as well as the Prieſts, as he calls them: that they were Miniſters not of the Spirit, but of the Letter only, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. that their Preaching was but with Wiſdom of Words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. with the inticing Words of Man's Wiſdom, <hi>ibid.</hi> 2.4. or at beſt but a Miniſtration of the Letter, not of the Spirit. (I do not write his Words, but his Senſe.) And this was an undeniable Evidence, and Demonſtration of the inſufficiency of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity Learning</hi> alone (alone I ſay) to qualifie Men to be Miniſters of Chriſt; for there were of both ſorts, thoſe who wanted not that, if that had been ſufficient: And if we inquire into the true reaſon of that, how that comes to paſs, ſince a principal End of our Univerſities is to qualifie Perſons for that Service, we ſhall preſently diſcover that, which is the Root, and true Cauſe, both of that, and of almoſt all the Unhappineſs of this Nation; and that is a great Defect, and <hi>Neglect of Teaching and Learning the best and chief part of all Learning and Knowledge;</hi> of true Heavenly Wiſdom. Their Learning is plainly ſuch an ineffectual Learning, which doth deceive their Souls, being void of the chief ſolid Food, like Chaff without the Corn, and Husks without the Kernel: it ſtops the Mouth, ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Stomach; but famiſheth the Soul: and not only ſo, but, like unwholſome Food, breeds
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40207:9"/>only Wind &amp; Crudities, a Knowledge that puffeth up, and Diſeaſes; a ſuperficial Notional Buſineſs, without any thing of true Culture and Food of Souls: a Form plainly without the Power; ſuch a Cheat and Deceit, as the moſt virulent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of any call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> could not exceed; but even Indignation would extort almoſt as much from a ſober Man duly ſenſible of it. It deceives themſelves; it deceives the People, whom they undertake to feed; and it deceives the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>The Teaching here is agreeable to <hi>the Deſign of thoſe who come to learn;</hi> a mixt Deſign of an unnatural Compoſure, Heaven and Earth, or rather Earth and Heaven; not ſo much God and Mammon, (which, according to our Saviour's Doctrine, are inconſiſtent) but Mammon and God; for the principal in the Deſign in this Caſe ought firſt to be named: and it is viſible in their Actions which that is; and even in their Common Expreſſions: for if one propoſe a Place with all the Advantages of doing Good that may be, preſently comes this filthy fulſome Queſtion; <hi>But what Encouragement is there?</hi> as if an Advantage for doing Good was not En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement enough to a Chriſtian to enter into the Service of God, without ſome humane aſſurance of I know not what temporal Income. And Preferments are not only thought, but plainly aſſerted to be the <hi>Encouragements of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40207:9"/>and I doubt they have their Reward. What <hi>unſatiable Greedineſs</hi> is obſervable gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in all, to be ſcandalous in almoſt the beſt, that can come at them! And what is the Uſe they make of them, when they have with great Study, and Pains, and Solicitations, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances, and Flatteries, and Coſts, at laſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them; but Pride, and Luxury, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies of Wives, and Children; to which all
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>v.</hi> Fa. Paul, Of Matters Beneficiary, <hi>N.</hi> 236, 237. &amp; ſ. <hi>a Sin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſpend that which exceeds the moderate Neceſſity of a Clergy-Man.</hi>
               </note> That muſt be ſacrificed, which was deſigned for Proviſion for true Food of Souls; of which Thouſands are daily famiſhed, for want of a competent number of duly qualified Labourers in the Lord's Vineyard, in the great Pariſhes about this City, and other parts of the Nation, where there is Maintenance enough, if ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were imployed, as did indeed make that their Buſineſs, Care and Concern. All their Learning raiſeth but few above the Senſual, to the Animal State; but none to the truly Spiritual: if any attain to that, it is by ſuch Means as may be uſed any where elſe, as well as at the Univerſity, as things are there ordered at preſent; and not by Univerſity Learning, which, as it is ordinarily uſed, doth more hinder than further it. Nor is it likely it ſhould have much better Effect upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which hath no better upon themſelves: For in the Spiritual Generation, as in the Carnal, Men beget their like; the ſtrong, ſuch as are ſtrong; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the weak and infirm, ſuch as themſelves are.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40207:10"/>
            <p>But if we look farther into <hi>the Concerns of the whole Nation,</hi> and their Duty to their Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in that reſpect, are not they to be both ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally and jointly, not only Paſtors, but Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; ſeverally over their own particular Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and jointly over the whole Nation? But what an inſignificant Generation are they, even the Chief of them in that reſpect, not only far ſhort of the Generoſity and Magnanimity of genuine Chriſtians, and the more immediate Servants of the Great Jehovah, but even of the natural Genius of their own Nation; as if their <hi>Preferments</hi> had ſome Narcotick and ſtupifying quality, or ſome ſecret Enchantment in them: And ſo in truth they have; they are like the <hi>Trojan Horſe;</hi> when they think they have got a great Prize, they themſelves are ſurprized and captivated by, they little think what, inviſible Enemies. When they return to the Pomps and Vanities of the World, which they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in their Baptiſm, they deſert the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Chriſtian State, and enter into the Power of the Enemy; and their true Chriſtian Strength departs from them: they have no longer any real ſtrength to ſerve the Lord Chriſt, but only ſuch an Appearance of it, as ſerves to deceive themſelves and others; and make them the more effectually ſubſervient to that Intereſt, which they do not deſign to ſerve: for their <hi>Actions and Behaviour</hi> render their <hi>Preaching</hi> not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40207:10"/>only ineffectual, but ſcandalous to Men, and ridiculous to the inviſible adverſe Powers, who are not a little gratified with the ſpectacle of it. It puts a Slight and Contempt upon the great and noble Examples of our Saviour, and the Ancient and moſt Heroick Chriſtians; but ſpreads the Devil's Snares, and decoys Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; promotes <hi>Chriſtian Idolatry,</hi> which is Covetouſneſs, to be as effectually deſtructive as any of the <hi>Jews</hi> ever was, or any of <hi>Papiſts</hi> can be; and tempts the World to believe, that either Earthly-mindedneſs, or to mind Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, is conſiſtent with Chriſtianity, or that they are no Chriſtians, and do not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves believe what they Preach unto others.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak a little more diſtinctly, there are <hi>two things to be conſider'd in our Engliſh Clergy;</hi> what they have originally from Chriſt, and what they have originally from Man. From <hi>Chriſt</hi> they have Authority to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, to teach and inſtruct the People, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacraments, and offer to God the ſolemn Prayers of the Church, to admoniſh, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and execute Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, where there is occaſion, and to receive the Oblations of the People for maintenance of themſelves, and for Pious Uſes; and a right to all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Submiſſion which is due to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt in ſo Holy an Imployment. And from <hi>Man,</hi> they have Houſes, and Lands,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40207:11"/>and Revenues, and Titles, and Honours, and Civil Power and Authority, and Charges and Incumbrances. And theſe are ſome good and uſeful; and ſome evil, pernicious, inconſiſtent with their Chriſtian State; and, to be plain, Antichriſtian. The Houſes, Lands, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues may be of good uſe, if they be uſed as they ſhould be; but the reſt are Antichriſtian, under pretence of Honouring, Degrading; and under pretence of enlarging their Power with what they had not, debaſing and abridging what they had, and ſubtilly enſlaving the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt to be Servants of Men; and not the outward Man only, but their very Minds and Spirits. And here lies the very <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity.</hi> They are deprived of one part of their Chriſtian Authority, and their Hands bound, under pretence of State and Grandure, by having Chancellors, like the Grandees of the World. They are ſubjected to the State by their Acceptance of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Dignities from thence, (the very Temptation that was offer'd by the Devil to our Saviour, and a betraying of the Rights of the Church of Chriſt.) And the Papal En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chroachments and Uſurpations being transferred to the Crown, and all Eccleſiaſtical Preferments coming from the King, this is firſt a <hi>Bait</hi> to allure Ambitious Minds, and then an <hi>Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> upon them, that they dare not diſpleaſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40207:11"/>the Creator of their Grandure, though for the Service of their true Lord and Maſter, and the Saviour of their Souls. So that we are like to have a continual Succeſſion of Flatterers of Princes, inſtead of faithful Monitors, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Servants of the great God to be; and Nurſeries of falſe Loyalty, inſtead of true Piety and Devotion to God; and of Inſtruments of inceſſant Diſſentions between Prince and People, inſtead of Healers of our Breaches; a juſt Judgment or deſerved conſequence of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge and Uſurpation upon the Church of Chriſt. And here, if I be not much miſtaken, lyeth <hi>the Root of all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſs of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and at this time in particular.</p>
            <p>The Providence of God hath not at any time been wanting to us; but we have been always wanting to our Duty to Him, and to our own true Intereſt. And though all have been wanting, yet the beginning of this defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency hath been in them, who ſhould have better attended to, and wiſely conſider'd the Motions of Providence, and been the firſt active vigorous Movers to the reſt to have correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with it: But, alas! they attended more to the Motions of Men, and to pleaſe them, or at leaſt not diſpleaſe them, for their own Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Security; and this is call'd Prudence forſooth: And ſo have we loſt a moſt favourable Opportunity put into our hands. When Men
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40207:12"/>turn from God to Men for Counſel, or Aſſiſtance, or Advancement, that Divine Power which doth ordinarily accompany the Ordinances and Orders of God, doth uſually depart from them, though choſen, or regularly commiſſioned by him; as it did from <hi>Saul:</hi> And then they are ready to fly to any mean things for ſupport or ſafety.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church of England</hi> hath been in <hi>Bondage,</hi> under the <hi>Civil Power,</hi> ever ſince it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from the <hi>Roman</hi> Uſurpations, which were not totally aboliſhed, but too much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to another Maſter; and a <hi>Slaviſh Spirit</hi> hath ever ſince poſſeſſed it. It did quietly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſs in the greateſt <hi>Sacriledge</hi> that ever was committed: It contentedly ſuffer'd the moſt ſolemn part of its <hi>Liturgy,</hi> compoſed by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops, and, as was declared by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the aid of the Holy Ghoſt, to be <hi>diſmember'd, diſorder'd, and defac'd,</hi> and the Chriſtian Sacrifice aboliſhed by Foreigners, and a Factious Party, which have ever ſince been Thorns in their Sides, without the concurrence of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy. The true Chriſtian <hi>Diſcipline</hi> they never had the Courage to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to reſtore, though an Office was prepar'd for a Memorial, with a Wiſh to have it reſtor'd, from the beginning, which King <hi>Charles</hi> II. obſerving upon an <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday,</hi> ask'd, <hi>Why do they not reſtore it? Who hinders 'em?</hi> And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40207:12"/>for the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, we have ordinarily on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mattens and Veſpers, and that too only on the Lord's-Day, and in that too the Prayers ſhort and deficient, either to excite, or to expreſs the Devotions of the People, where there is any; and beſides all this, what we have, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly read with ſo little Devotion, as gives Scandal to many, and no little diſturbance to others. And our very <hi>Sacraments</hi> and moſt Holy Things, no leſs than Holy-Days, are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly prophaned. <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which is the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of our engaging in the Chriſtian Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, not only permitted, but even forced upon ſuch as do not deſire it, either for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or their Children; but bring their Infant Children either for fear of the Apparator, or out of Cuſtom to be like their Neighbours, without any ſenſe or underſtanding of ſo much of the Chriſtian Religion as was required anciently of Catechumens, before they were admitted to <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> And that other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Holy Memorials of our Saviour's Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which, from the riſing of the Sun to the ſetting of it, that is, all over the World, hath, in all Aſſemblies of Chriſtians, for the ſolemn Worſhip of God, till the laſt Age, been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before God, as a ſolemn Recognition of our Redemption by Chriſt, and Subjection to him as our Lord, hath been not only moſt ſhamefully neglected, and ſo treated, both
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40207:13"/>in Sermons from the Pulpit, and in Printed Books, that it appears few amongſt us rightly underſtand it at this day; but moſt horribly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fan'd, not only by common admittance of all that will to it, but even forcing the moſt wicked and profane Officers to it, upon the Penalty of loſing their Places. And ſo unhappily have ſome of our Controverſies with <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks</hi> been managed, and ſo ſuperficially and impertinently our Preaching been generally throughout the Nation, that we have diſputed one part, into disbelief of the Scriptures and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity; another, into contempt of one of the chief Principles of Chriſtianity; and generally all, into Neglect and Contempt of the Examples, Precepts, and Counſels of greateſt Perfection in the Chriſtian Religion; and together with that, preached the People generally into a careleſs tepid ſtate of Indifferency; ſo that in the Country eſpecially, it is rare to meet with two or three good ſenſible intelligent lively Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in a Pariſh. And who of our principal Clergy can deny any of this? And if it be all true, why is it not reformed? If they cannot reform all, why not as much as they can? Why is not the <hi>Chriſtian Worſhip</hi> reſtored in their Cathedrals? And if thoſe be ſo burden'd by prophane Officers impoſed upon them, that they fear to expoſe it, why do they not reform their own Families, and reſtore it at leaſt in their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40207:13"/>own Chappels? What Account will this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church, as carnal Flatterers call it, give of their Neglect of Propagating the Goſpel in Foreign parts, at leaſt in our own Plantations, and ſuffering them to be ſuch Nourſeries of Scandals to the Infidels? What Account of the many things fit to be done at home, for the Service of their Maſter; and fit to be conſidered by them jointly in a Body, and promoted in Parliament; which yet are neither ſtudied, nor conſidered, nor ſo much as thought on by any of them, no more than if they did not belong to their Care, or were not of any Concern to their Maſter, though they ſit Seſſion after Seſſion in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? But how can it be expected that they ſhould ever extend their care to things ſo remote, who take no more care of what doth concern them in their own Chappels and Families?</p>
            <p>It is an amazing thing for one whoſe Eyes are open, to conſider theſe things. But it fairs with collective Bodies of Men, as with ſingle Perſons: they are ſubject to the like Diſeaſes: the State of this Church is plainly a Tepid, Scorbutick, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinarian, Laodicean State, quite ſick of the Prudentials; and has been ſo in a manner from the firſt Settlement of the Reformation. And to ſpeak freely, as becomes an honeſt Man, though there was great need of a Reformation, when it was begun by <hi>Luther,</hi> and long before; yet hath that great Work been ſo ill managed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40207:14"/>with more of the Antichriſtian than Chriſtian Spirit, that I cannot ſee, by any growth in Grace and Virtue, that the Bleſſing of God hath ever been with it; only he ſeems to have preſerved theſe Reformations rather as Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Corrections for the Obſtinacy of that Church which would not reform: and raiſed up and preſerved the ſeveral Sub-diviſions of Parties amongſt us for the very ſame cauſe and purpoſe. For <hi>the True Cauſe of all the Diviſions and Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations amongst us,</hi> is no other but our Scandals, Abuſes and Corruptions; both by way of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Cauſation, and by the ſpecial Judgment of God, to awaken us, if it be poſſible. And though the Bleſſing of God, the true Spiritual Chriſtian Bleſſing, be not upon them, becauſe he doth not favour <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Diviſions,</hi> yet is his Protection over them, as his Inſtruments in the Nature of a Judgment, and in ſome things to raiſe an Emulation in thoſe of the Church, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they would lay it to heart and underſtand it For there is none of them all, but there is ſome thing in them, which may ſerve for Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Notice of ſomething amiſs in the Church.</p>
            <p>This which I have now ſaid, may be of uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not only to them of the Church, but alſo to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the ſeveral ſeparate Parties,</hi> and deſerve thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very ſerious and deep Conſideration. For it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not a light matter <hi>to Make a Schiſm or Diviſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in any particular Church, or in the Catholic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40207:14"/>Church. It hath been looked upon, in all Ages, to be a <hi>damnable</hi> Sin: and who-ever doth well conſider the ſeveral weighty Admonitions in the Scriptures concerning it, if he have not a benumed Conſcience, will not make light of it; nor yield to plauſible pretences: there is nothing ſo bad, but the Wit of Man and ſubtile Suggeſtions of Satan can put a colour upon it; nor ſo good, but they can miſ-repreſent it and diſparage it: but it is dangerous and very imprudent to play tricks with Sacred things. Any thing elſe may be more ſafely medled with in that manner.</p>
            <p>This does concern them all in general; and I muſt add a word or two more: There are none of the beſt of them, that I have yet talked with, that could or would deny that their Party was much ſunk in Piety and Virtue from thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of it, which was in thoſe before them of the ſame Party. And this being ſo, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us all to conſider well, whether the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy</hi> foretold be not an Apoſtacy in Practice, as well as in Principles? and, Whether, while we are gazing to ſee the Judgments of God upon it abroad, it may not be found amongſt us at home; and we feel, in a ſurprize upon the Nation at home, what we expect to ſee elſewhere, at <hi>Rome;</hi> as was upon this City in <hi>ſixty ſix.</hi> And certain I am, that there are not only <hi>Antichriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> amongſt us all, but whole <hi>Antichriſtian Sects and Parties,</hi> which, deceived by the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40207:15"/>of Satan, under the moſt ſpecious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of the moſt pure and refined Chriſtianity, do undermine and enervate the true Genuine Chriſtianity, and the Power of Godlineſs. It is one of <hi>the Devil's</hi> moſt ſubtile <hi>Policies,</hi> by abuſe of Scripture, and miſ-application of certain Truths, to impoſe upon People, and overturn them. So he began with our Saviour, and ſo he goes on with Profeſſors to and at this day. The Holy Scriptures are abuſed, the Honour of God is abuſed, the Merits of Chriſt are abuſed, the Guidance of the Spirit is abuſed, the Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Condeſcention of the Goſpel is abuſed, and whatever is moſt Excellent and Admirable is abuſed by the Subtilty of the Enemy, and the ſupine Negligence, and Inconſiderateneſs and Folly of Men. And woe be to them who dare preſume to be the Inſtruments and Leaders in theſe Abuſes and Doctrines.</p>
            <p>It is certain that our Saviour gave Inſtructions to his Apoſtles for the Settling of his Church; and that they accordingly in all places, where there were a competent number of Converts, did ordain Elders, and gave Authority to others to do the like; and ſo ſettled a <hi>Succeſſion</hi> in the Church, which hath continued all over the World to this day. And it is certain, that the State of the <hi>Jews</hi> was ſo corrupted in his time, as provoked the Judgment of God upon them, ſo that they are a Monument thereof all over
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40207:15"/>the World to this day; and yet neither He, nor his Diſciples, did ever refuſe communion with them, till they were caſt out; and ſo far was he from allowing them to ſeparate, that he foretold their being caſt out of the Synagogues, as part of the Perſecution they were to ſuffer. It is alſo certain, that our Saviour did foretell that many falſe Prophets, <hi>that is,</hi> falſe Teachers, ſhould come in his Name, and deceive many; and gave great Caution not to go out or believe them; and that his Apoſtles did the like, and did with great earneſtneſs exhort all to beware of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Schiſms, and Separations in the Church: And accordingly, in all Ages, for Men to take upon them the Office of Elders or Miniſters of the Goſpel, without a Regular Ordination, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived by Succeſſion from the Apoſtles; or to draw away people after them, and engage them in Separate Parties, hath been looked upon as a heinous Sin; and whoever have done ſo have been Infamous in the Church ever ſince. And therefore, if our Diſſenters did continue daily with one accord at our Temples, as the primitive Chriſtians did, and did continue their Aſſemblies at their own Meeting-places, for Inſtruction and Edification, without any Separation from the Church, provided there was nothing but true Chriſtian Doctrine taught amongſt them, I do not ſee but they might be of very good Uſe, and deſerve not only an Indulgence, but Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40207:16"/>from the Publick Authority. But they, who make a Trade of it to engage Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Parties, I do verily believe have much to anſwer for before God: and thoſe who deſire to be Chriſtians indeed, had need to beware of them. And this I muſt in juſtice ſay, after all I have ſaid concerning what is amiſs amongſt us, that, thanks be to God, we have thoſe amongſt us, who, for good Learning, for profitable Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and for ſincere Piety, Devotion, and all Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, are no way inferior to any of the Diſſenters, if to be equalled by any of them: and yet I cannot ſay they are ſo many, but there may be reaſon enough to receive thoſe Labourers alſo into our Lord's Harveſt. And I heartily wiſh it was well conſidered, How they may be made more ſerviceable in ſo important and needful a Work, without any thing of a Separation: and that they would conſider, Who They are, who ſit in <hi>Moſes,</hi> or rather the Apoſtles Seat, and, What our Lord doth require in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>And now, to come more particularly to the PEOPLE of that Party call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> I muſt firſt acquaint them, that I have not only had ſeveral <hi>Conferences,</hi> with the Principal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Party, whom they call <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but have alſo ſent them ſeveral <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> to their Second Days Meetings: And as our Conferences have hitherto been managed in a very friendly manner, ſo I do deſire to proceed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40207:16"/>in the ſame manner with them alſo: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what is directed at firſt only to the ſecond days Meeting, I ſhall deſire them now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as intended from the firſt for them all, though I thought it moſt fair and decent to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in that order. And it is as followeth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To</hi> William Penn, <hi>and the reſt of the Friends with him, at their ſecond days Meeting in</hi> Grace-Church-Street.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>William,</hi> and the reſt of the Friends with thee,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MY Hearts deſire and Prayer to God for you all, is, that ye may be ſaved: for I am perſwaded that you have a Zeal of God, at least many of you, though not according to Knowledge in ſome things. Nevertheleſs, whereto ye have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, in that I deſire ye may be eſtabliſhed, and that God will be graciouſly pleaſed to reveal the rest to you, that ye may be perfect and intire, want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing. For which purpoſe I come, I trust, by the Grace of God, with a Meſſage of Grace and Peace to you. I am well ſatisfied that it is no meer Humane Project or Artifice, that at first raiſed you up, and hath conducted you hitherto: but a Supernatural Power, and that it is of the Lord, ſome way or other, (as was the Separation
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40207:17"/>of the Ten Tribes from</hi> Rehoboam, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>for Correction and Reformation of ſomething ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in this Church. And therefore I dare not preſume either upon my own head, or by my own Ability, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> intermeddle in it. But my Heart is inlarged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you upon theſe Conſiderations:</hi> 1. <hi>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ye do aſſert one of the Great and Chief Principle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the Chriſtian Religion, which I have obſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to be very unworthily and even deſpitefully treated by too many, who have gotten into, or ſeek, Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Imployment in the Church, without Chec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> or Reproof; and ſo unworthily deſerted by most for fear of reproach, or diſgrace, or hindrance in their Preferment, that I have not known it gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly aſſerted by above two or three in the Pulpit, (but thoſe great Men indeed) though it be plainly a Doctrine moſt authentickly and ſolemnly profeſſed and declared in the</hi> Church of England. 2. <hi>That ye do bear a good Teſtimony againſt other Abuſes connived at, or tolerated amongſt us.</hi> 3. <hi>I am moved with Pity towards you, that you ſhould have ſo great Cauſes of Offence or Scandal given you, againſt the Holy and Eſtabliſhed Inſtitutions and Ordinances of Chriſt, for the Miniſterial Office; for the Admiſſion of Proſelytes; and for the great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the Chriſtian Worſhip, which hath been ſo long abuſed with Controverſies, that I know very few Perſons now amongſt us, who do rightly and compleatly underſtand it; and even againſt the Perſon, Satisfaction, and Merits of Chriſt himſelf.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40207:17"/>But when I conſider your Notions and Sentiments concerning theſe things, though I am well ſatisfied that you are under the Conduct and Energy of ſome Spiritual Power; yet,</hi> What that Spirit is? <hi>and,</hi> Whether One or Divers? <hi>in my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doth deſerve very good Conſideration. Ye know what Spirit it was, which God ſent between</hi> Abimelech <hi>and the</hi> Shechemites, <hi>Jud.</hi> 9.23. <hi>and what that was, that was ſent from the Lord to</hi> Saul, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.14. <hi>and what that was, that was commiſſioned by God in the caſe of</hi> Ahab, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22, 23. <hi>and what that was, in the midſt of the Princes of</hi> Noph, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.14. <hi>which was from the Lord too. And that ſuch a Spirit hath been among ſome call'd</hi> Quakers, <hi>is manifeſt both by their Actions, Speeches, and Writings; nay, the very Spirit of the Devil, and of Antichriſt, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and undeniable, from the Indignities offered both in word and deed, to Holy things. But that is not the thing now to be conſidered, what Spirits may have appeared among them. For even among the Apoſtles, Satan had power to enter into</hi> Judas; <hi>and it is not improbable but thoſe, whom our Saviour told,</hi> Ye know not what Spirit ye are of; <hi>and even</hi> Peter <hi>himſelf, when our Saviour ſaid to him,</hi> Get thee behind me, Satan, <hi>might not at the time be free from ſome Impreſſions of Evil Spirits. That, 'tis likely, was a Peculiarity of our Saviour's, or the Prince of this World to have nothing in him. But the thing to be conſidered, is,</hi> What Spirit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40207:18"/>that is which at firſt excited, and hath now the Conduct of the whole Body of this People? <hi>And, not, whether it be ſent, or commiſſioned from God? but,</hi> Whether <hi>it be</hi> one of the Miniſtring Spirits <hi>ſent forth to miniſter for them, who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation? or,</hi> One of thoſe Seducing Spirits, <hi>to whom, in the latter times, that ſome would give heed, was, in the times of the Apoſtles, expreſsly ſaid by the Spirit of God? And great</hi> Reaſon <hi>there is to take this into very deep Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration:</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe of the many and weighty</hi> Cautions <hi>given by our Saviour and his Apoſtles, and left upon record in the Sacred Scriptures, for our warning in theſe latter times, to beware of them, and not to go out after them; with</hi> Admonitions <hi>concerning their Subtilty, their Energy or Power, and their ſtrong Deluſions to deceive, if it were poſſible, the very Elect; and that even Satan him ſelf is transformed into an Angel of Light, that is puts on the Appearance of an Angel of Light</hi> (2 Cor. 11.14.) <hi>and, laſtly, that we ſhould tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Spirits,</hi> (1 Jo. 4.1.) 2. <hi>Becauſe, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Tryal <hi>be by Agreement or Diſagreement with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Doctrine, Inſtitutions and Ordinances of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles-authorized by him, they may ſeem t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> have apoſtatized and gone off, or, at leaſt, falle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhort of them, in matters of great Moment, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſpecial concern, thoſe before mentioned; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> therefore to be Seduced by ſome</hi> Spirit of Error<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>For I doubt not but the Devil himſelf hath th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:40207:18"/>Malice and Envy againſt the Man Chriſt Jeſus, by whom he hath been Conquered and Vanquiſhed, and againſt the Solemn Memorial of that Victory, that could he but keep people from engaging in that Holy Covenant with Him by Baptiſm, and from the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that Memorial, he would be willing himſelf to lead them into all other Truth, upon that condition, rather than fail. Yet notwithſtanding, ſince they are a Sober People, have received, retained, and do act upon one of the chief Principles of Chriſtianity, and have divers commendable things in them; and what Errors they have fallen into, have been occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the Scandals and Offences given by thoſe of the Church, who will have a ſad account to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for it: I do hope in the Mercy and Goodneſs of God, that if it be a good Spirit, which hath the Conduct of them, he ſhall lead and diſpoſe thoſe who are Sincere amongſt them, to the acknowledgment of the Truth in thoſe things, whereto they have not yet attained; and if it be otherwiſe, he ſhall be forced to reſign the Conduct of them to a more powerful and better Guide; and that we ſhall ſee ſuch a Society of</hi> Compleat Chriſtians <hi>come out of this deſpiſed People, as are at this time hardly to be found in any part of the World, that I know of. Theſe are my Thoughts, and Hopes concerning this People in general at preſent. And Hopes, I ſay, grounded upon the Mercy of God, and Power of God, which no Good Being would oppoſe; nor no Evil Power can ſtand before. And in His Name I come
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40207:19"/>unto you, knowing aſſuredly that neither I, nor any Humane Ability, is able to prevail againſt the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that is amongſt you, notwithſtanding the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Truths that I have mentioned already, and ſhall endeavour, by the Grace and Aſſiſtance of God Almighty, through our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, more fully to explain unto you in due time: But, as I ſaid, if it be a good Power, it will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour me and aſſiſt me in it, and rejoyce in it too: and if it be an Evil Power Commiſſioned, it muſt ceaſe, and ſubmit to that Victorious and All-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Name: Its Enchantments muſt be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and its Sophiſtry and Falacies detected. I therefore, as an Ambaſſador of Chriſt, in the Spirit and Meekneſs of Chriſt, beſeech you, Be ye reconciled to the Truths of God, and receive them with that Reverence and Gratitude that is meet, without Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, or regard to any Temporal concern. I do not invite you to return to the Abuſes and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which you have forſaken, but to thoſe Truths, and to the due uſe of thoſe Holy things, againſt which you have been Scandalized by thoſe Abuſes and Corruptions. Nor do I invite you to diſſolve your Society, or to leave off your Meetings, and drown your ſelves in a promiſcuous Multitude. No, you have in part born a good Teſtimony, and I would have you do ſo ſtill: But I invite you only to make your Teſtimony more Compleat, Illuſtrious, and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable, by bearing your Teſtimony to the whole Truth; and not any longer a Teſtimony like the Feet
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40207:19"/>of</hi> Daniel<hi>'s Image, partly ſtrong, and partly weak, by a mixture of Truth with Falſhood; for that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand long together; but to ſtrengthen the things that remain, and ſet in order the things that are wanting, that ye may ſtand; for otherwiſe ye will certainly be Broken to Pieces. I invite you but to what I am doing my ſelf with a ſmall Company of Poor people, that is bearing a Teſtimony for God, and manifeſtly under his Conduct: But it is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by them, to whom it hath been offered for a ſufficient Time, and in a ſufficient Manner, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Learning, and pretence to Knowledge: And now it is offered to you, a deſpiſed People, that God may humble the Proud and High-minded, and confound the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, by mean and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable things, in the ſight of Men. Be Wiſe, and neglect not the Opportunity, and you, who were laſt in the Worlds account, ſhall be firſt. What ever you do, you will find there is ſolid Truth in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and I wiſh you may receive it to the Honour and Glory of God, and your own Comfort and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and you will then find me to have been</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Sincere and Cordial Friend,<hi>E. S.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>31 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1696.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40207:20"/>
            <p>After this there were other Letters and Papers ſent, which may be taken notice of hereafter, as there may be occaſion; but the laſt contained <hi>certain Queſtions,</hi> which I think fit now to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the Conſideration of all, who are ſincere, and do deſire not to deceive themſelves, nor be deceived in a matter of ſo great Importance, as the Will and Service of God, and the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own Souls. If any notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will preſume to go on in any falſe or Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Ways, they muſt anſwer for it, and their Blood, if they miſcarry, muſt be upon their own Heads. For <hi>the Deſign and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of theſe Queſtions</hi> is, to examin the caſe, What Spirit they are of? the Spirit of Chriſt, or the Spirit of Antichriſt; the Spirit of Truth, or ſome ſubtile Spirit of Deluſion? Whether they be Chriſtians indeed, or counterfeit Chriſtians, <hi>that is,</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians? Whether Hypocritical Profeſſors in Words, but Renagadoes in Deeds, refuſing the Solemnities of his Covenant and Worſhip, and the Orders of his Church, or ſuch ſincere Chriſtians as are ready to follow the Guidance of his Spirit out of their own Wills, and out of their own Wiſdom and Imaginations, and Errors and Miſtakes, into all Truth? and, Whether they be in the Way of Salvation, or of Deluſion and Perdition? <hi>The Times of this Ignorance God winked at, but now commandeth all Men every where to Repent.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:40207:20"/>
            <head>QUESTIONS PROPOSED To the People call'd QUAKERS, Firſt to their Miniſters, at their <hi>ſecond days</hi> Meeting; and now, to them All; for the better Examination, and rectifying ſome <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes</hi> amongſt them.</head>
            <p n="1">I. WHether there be not a great Party of <hi>fallen Angels and wicked Spirits,</hi> which are Enemies to Mankind, and with all the Power, Activity, and Subtilty they can, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually endeavour to hinder their Salvation, and Communion and Union with the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit?</p>
            <p n="2">II. Whether <hi>the Word,</hi> which in the beginning was with God, and was God, was not <hi>made Fleſh</hi> and dwelt amongſt Men, being born of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40207:21"/>the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and called <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Saviour, and <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the anointed of God, and <hi>Jeſus Christ of Nazareth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Whether <hi>his Appearance</hi> in Mortal Fleſh was not <hi>to deſtroy the Works of the Devil,</hi> the Prince of that Party of fallen Angels and wicked Spirits; to be a Prince and a Saviour to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and the Captain of their Salvation to all who receive him, and ſubject themſelves intirely to his Teachings by his Example, and by his Doctrine, and Precepts, and Orders recorded in the Holy Scriptures, and by the Motions of his Holy Spirit upon and in their Hearts and Minds?</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Whether he be not the <hi>Only Mediatour</hi> between God and Man; ſo that Man can have no Communion with the Holy God, or Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the Spirit of Holineſs, but by and through Him?</p>
            <p n="5">V. Whether that Party of <hi>fallen Angels and wicked Spirits,</hi> knowing this, do not above all things <hi>endeavour,</hi> by all means, <hi>to with-hold peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from cloſing and uniting with that Holy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour,</hi> and to withdraw as many as they can as much as they can from Him?</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Whether <hi>their most dangerous and ſubtile Actings</hi> in this Oppoſition be not principally, <hi>by Way of Deceit,</hi> under the Appearance and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Good to Man, and of Good Spirits?</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Whether it hath not been fore-told, that, in the latter times eſpecially, there ſhould be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40207:21"/>many <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> who, with ſuch ſpecious Pretences and ſecret Energy, ſhould endeavour to draw away People from the Faith, as to deceive, if it was poſſible, the very Elect; and Warnings given to beware of them, by Chriſt and by his Apoſtles?</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Whether <hi>the Spirit of God</hi> and <hi>the Spirit of Christ</hi> be not the ſame, and a Holy and Pure Spirit, a Spirit of Truth and Righteouſneſs, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into all neceſſary Truth, and from all Fraud, Deceit, and Falacy, Cavils, and ſhuffling Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions?</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Whether it be not reaſonable <hi>that Christ Jeſus,</hi> who had done ſo much for Man, ſhould <hi>preſcribe</hi> what Manner he pleaſed for his Peoples engaging with Him; and for their recognizing Him, and making their Solemn Addreſs to the Father by Him; and what Orders he pleaſed and would have obſerved and continued in his Church?</p>
            <p n="10">X. Whether <hi>to oppoſe</hi> ſuch Appointments, Preſcriptions or Orders, <hi>or to cavil</hi> at them, ſeek Evaſions or Pretences to neglect them, and yet pretend to be Chriſtians, be not a great Evidence of Inſincerity, and of a ſubtile Antichriſtian Spirit of Satan transformed into an Angel of Light?</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Whether Jeſus Chriſt, beſides his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Command to his Apoſtles after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, to go to the <hi>Gentiles, and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40207:22"/>baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost,</hi> &amp;c. did not for <hi>forty days</hi> ſhew himſelf to them, <hi>ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God,</hi> until the day in which he was taken up, after that he, through the Holy Ghoſt, had given Commandments unto them, and in or with thoſe <hi>Commandments</hi> give them ſufficient <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Directions</hi> for the Conſtituting his Church, which he purchaſed with his Blood?</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Whether the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did not in all things <hi>faithfully purſue</hi> his Commands and Directions?</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Whether beſides his expreſs Commands and Directions, they did not alſo <hi>receive the Holy Spirit,</hi> according to his Promiſe in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner, and had the ſame <hi>reſiding in them,</hi> and <hi>manifeſting his Preſence</hi> with them, by extraordinary Operations, to guide and aſſiſt them in their Work?</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Whether they having received the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to make Diſciples in all Nations, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi>) baptizing them, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever he commanded them, did not in all places preach the Goſpel, exhort the People to believe and be <hi>baptized,</hi> and baptized with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe, who did believe, though baptized before with <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and though they had received the Holy Spirit, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:40207:22"/>
            <p n="15">XV. Whether the Apoſtles, and the People converted by them, after they had received the Holy Ghoſt, did not, when they came together in one, or aſſembled for the Solemn Worſhip of God, <hi>break Bread,</hi> and <hi>eat the Lord's Supper,</hi> and do as their Lord did, and commanded them to do; and that ſo conſtantly, that there is not known any Aſſembly of Chriſtians in the time of the Apoſtles, nor in many Ages after, to have been held for the Solemn Worſhip of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it?</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. Whether the Apoſtles did not <hi>ordain Elders,</hi> and appoint others, by ſpecial Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, to do the ſame, in every City; by ſuch Authority, that none did preſume to take the Office of <hi>Elder</hi> unto himſelf, but who was ſo ordained; or the Office of <hi>Ordaining Elders,</hi> but who was ſo appointed, either in the times of the Apoſtles, or afterward, but who have been infamous ever ſince?</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Whether ſeeing that our Saviour himſelf, though he needed not, would notwithſtanding be baptized with Water, to fulfill all Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and thereupon had ſenſible Approbation from Heaven, did alſo by his Apoſtles baptize with Water; and that it is plain by their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that his Apoſtles, and the whole Church of Chriſt, did underſtand his Command to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize all Nations, of Baptiſm by Water, and as neceſſary for Forgiveneſs of Sins; and that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40207:23"/>with the Holy Ghoſt was peculiar to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: whether, I ſay, this being ſo, it be not a forced and ſtrained Interpretation, without any ſound ground, and contrary to the moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Means of explaining Words, to reſtrain that Command to Baptiſm by the Holy Ghoſt only?</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Whether, if ſuch Conſtruction be by any Spirit more than humane, it be not the Spirit of Antichriſt or Satan transformed, to with-hold Men under his own Dominion, from ſolemnly ingaging with Chriſt, and from Forgiveneſs of their Sins in his Name? or, If it be only by Opinion of Men, ſuch Opinion obſtinately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in, be not a Damnable Sin, contrary to ſubjection of all Imaginations to the Obedience of Chriſt, and ſubverting of Souls, and ſuch Teachers to be abominated and anathamatized by all ſincere Chriſtians, as Seducers, and the Miniſters and Inſtruments of Satan, though they appear in Sheeps cloathing?</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. Whether, it having been the conſtant belief of all Nations, (whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles</hi>) that they had a real, though Spiritual, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Gods they worſhipped, in their Participation of their Sacrifices, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. and may be proved by good Authority; and Chriſtians duly diſpoſed, having a like Communion with Chriſt in the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the conſecrated Bread and Cup, as St.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40207:23"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> affirms; and the ſolemn Worſhipping of God, by preſenting our Prayers to the Father, with thoſe Memorals of our Saviour's Paſſion, being plainly a Recognition of our Redemption by Chriſt, and of his Dominion over us, acquired by his Paſſion, and that that is the only Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation, and He the only Mediator, by which, and by whom we Mortals born in Sin can have Acceſs to, and Acceptance with the Father; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> having received the Doctrine of what he taught concerning this, from the Lord; and the ancient Chriſtians frequenting this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, after they had manifeſtly received the Holy Ghoſt: Whether, I ſay, this being ſo, to reject theſe either as Types and Shadows, (which are indeed Antitypes, as the <hi>Grecians</hi> expreſs it, Solemn Memorials, and Senſible Declarations before God, Angels and Men, of preſent inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal actions of our Minds, for the greater Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation and Notoriety of the Fact) be not meer Sophiſtry, Shuffle and Evaſion; or as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, upon pretence that Chriſt is come to them in the Spirit; or of their having the Subſtance; be not to ſet up themſelves in Pride above the Apoſtles and Holy Chriſtians, who had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly the Spirit of God; nay, above Chriſt himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> to reject that as needleſs, which he inſtituted as neceſſary; and a plain Evidence of the Subtilty and Deluſion of Satan, to oppoſe Chriſt, and detain and withdraw people from his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40207:24"/>Solemn Worſhip, and under the moſt ſpecious appearance of the Spirit of God, by ſenſible Motions to things appearing Good, and by Falſe Lights, to corrupt and adulterate them, and get and keep a reſidence in them, as if it was the Spirit of Chriſt? Whether ſuch Obſtinacy, ſuch Fallacy, in ſuch a Matter, of ſuch Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in Chriſtianity, and yet ſo eaſie to Man, and void of all Exceptions, be not plain Evidence of a Myſtery of Iniquity in it?</p>
            <p n="20">XX. Whether to deliver thoſe things in the Name of the Lord, as immediately from the Lord, and by his Spirit, which may be plainly perceived and detected to proceed either from a humane Spirit, or a Spirit of Error, be not a great Preſumption againſt the Holy Majeſty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and a great Scandal to the Holy Doctrine of the Guidance of the Spirit of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a double and great Sin; the Sin of the Falſe Prophets of old, and that which in <hi>Germany</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and ſince in this Nation, raiſed ſo great a Prejudice againſt the Truth?</p>
            <p>Upon the peruſal of theſe Queſtions, it may be ſuppoſed that ſome <hi>Anſwer</hi> was returned, and therefore ſome account of that may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be expected; and I ſhould have been glad to have been able to have anſwered ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable an Expectation more fully: but the truth in ſhort is, that eight of the firſt ten were
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40207:24"/>anſwered affirmatively, but the other two were anſwered indeed, but with Anſwers not to the Queſtions: and the other ten remain yet to be anſwered; but I hope upon due conſideration will be anſwered at laſt, not with words only, but with deliberate ſolemn Actions. Nor are my <hi>Hopes</hi> without <hi>rational Ground.</hi> For in the ſeveral <hi>Conferences</hi> I have had with them, ſeven or eight at a time, of the principal leading Men of their Party, they behaved themſelves, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſerious conſiderate Perſons; heard patiently and attentively, replyed gravely and calmly, none interrupting either me or any of their own party while ſpeaking; and our Concluſion was friendly, though not altogether agreeing in the ſame Sentiments. And this is my Ground in reſpect of the <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Matter</hi> it ſelf in queſtion, That they have been led into Error and Miſtake in ſome things, the due Conſideration of theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions will in a great meaſure make them ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And when, beſides, they ſhall conſider by what Means they, who miſled the reſt, came to overſhoot themſelves, and fall into thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, <hi>viz.</hi> through the Scandals before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and that common Infirmity incident to us Mortals, to run from one Extream into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this will farther ſatisfie and confirm them in the truth of it. And if to theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be added a clear Explication of the Truth,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40207:25"/>which they did not rightly apprehend before this, with the Grace of God, will farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the Mind of thoſe, who are ſincere, and regard Truth more than any temporal Concern, with much Satisfaction, <hi>viz.</hi> That Baptizm with Water, and that <hi>Noble Solemnity of the Chriſtian Worſhip,</hi> are not needleſs <hi>Types and Shadows</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things paſt and fulfilled, as they imagin, but So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Expreſſions and Declarations, more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſively and remarkably ſignificative than Words, before God, Angels, Devils and Men, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſent Acts of the Mind, of what is internally and inviſibly at the ſame inſtant acted in Spirit; the one, of our <hi>Engagement in an Holy Covenant with God in Chriſt,</hi> by putting off, by Repentance, our Pollutions through Sin, and Dedication of our Selves to the Holy Trinity; the other, of our <hi>Recognition</hi> of our Redemption by Chriſt, by his Death and Sacrifice upon the Croſs, and of his Dominion over us, and our Subjection to Him, even to lay down our Lives in Obedience to Him, as he did His in Obedience to his Father which is done by making our Solemn Addreſs, and preſenting our Prayers to the Father, with the Memorials of his Paſſion, as the Great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for the Sins of Mankind, and Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of thoſe Memorials, being Conſecrated not only by a Separation to a Holy Uſe, but by a real Sanctification through the Spirit of God at the Prayers of the Church, whereby the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40207:25"/>Faithful have a real and Spiritual Communion with Him, and one with another. This is the pure Offering of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> foretold by <hi>Malachy,</hi> That it ſhould be Offer'd by them from the riſing of the Sun, even unto the going down of the ſame. And this is the Senſe and Meaning thereof received and retained by the Church of Chriſt all over the World, till <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi>'s new Notions became received as the Pure Word of God, and made this moſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime, moſt Holy, and moſt Auguſt Sacrament, as it is deſervedly call'd by Dr. <hi>Morton,</hi> be taken in effect for a needleſs Ceremony, or of no great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, by others beſides the Quakers, and uſed, or rather neglected, accordingly even to this day. Theſe are the great things in it, which I have now mentioned, but rare to be found in our Books now a days, or heard of from our Pulpits: Nor can it conveniently here be explained as it deſerves. But as to both theſe, what is ſaid before, <hi>pag.</hi> 13, 14. ought to be conſider'd. Theſe things, I ſay, well conſider'd, cannot chooſe but make great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon the Minds of thoſe who are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and have a due ſenſe of their own Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Eternal concerns.</p>
            <p>But when they ſhall alſo underſtand, That the great Principle of the <hi>Guidance of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of God, is not ſo peculiar to themſelves as they imagin, but the conſtant Doctrine of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40207:26"/>
               <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> in all Ages, and of the <hi>Church of England</hi> in particular, (as I have ſhew'd in a Diſcourſe of <hi>Myſtical Divinity,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under the Title of <hi>Aſceticks, or the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Piety and Vertue of the Ancients,</hi>) and notwithſtanding the Extravagancies of ſome inconſiderate Oppoſers of Fanaticiſm, aſſerted by moſt eminent Men of this <hi>Church,</hi> as the profound Dr. <hi>Cradock,</hi> lately deceaſed, (who himſelf told me, he had Preached twenty or thirty Sermons upon that Subject) and others now living; and that there are and have been, before <hi>George Fox</hi> appeared in the World, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Communion of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as well acquainted with Spiritual things as themſelves; and, by conſequence, how little neceſſity there is of venturing upon the Sin of Schiſm for that cauſe: And moreover conſider, that Chriſt appointed an <hi>Order of Men</hi> for his Miniſterial Office <hi>to ſucceed in his Church</hi> by an external Call and Commiſſion; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Corruptions of thoſe who ſate then in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Seat, would not ſuffer his Diſciples to break Communion with them, or diſregard their Authority; and by conſequence how dangerous it may prove in the end, for Men to preſume to ſet up Parties, and draw People after them contrary to his Orders, and to continue ſo to do, after fair Warnings and unanſwerable Admonitions to the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:40207:26"/>
            <p>To conclude, When they ſhall farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how horrid a Sin it muſt needs be to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to attribute to the Holy Spirit of God, the Workings of their own Imaginations, or perhaps the Subtile Suggeſtions of ſome wicked Spirit of Deluſion; and to expoſe and ſcandalize the Holy Doctrine of the Guidance of the Holy Spirit, by denying of certain and manifeſt Truths; and uſing ſuch little Shifts and Evaſions to oppoſe plain Evidence, as an honeſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Lawyer would ſcorn and be aſhamed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe for his Client: When all theſe things, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore that might be obſerved, are well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and conſidered, why may I not with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on hope that all, who are really ſuch as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave appeared, in the ſeveral Conferences I have had with them, to be, ſhould anſwer the End of my Letters and Queſtions, with more than civil and kind Words, in real and ſolemn Actions? Why ſhould I not hope that no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate Intereſt, nor any Temporal Concern, ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inder them? Why ſhould I not hope, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce God hath apparently again concluded all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder Sin, (which all Parties confeſs of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers but their own, and is true of all without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xception) that all ſhould humble themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore Him, return to mutual Charity one with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother, and ſubject themſelves, and all their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>maginations, to his Wiſdom, as well as their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions to his Will, to the intent that he may
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40207:27"/>have Mercy upon all? Why ſhould I not hope I ſay, ſince God hath done this, and for thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> End, that they, if they be indeed partake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his Holy Spirit, ſhould be the firſt in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glory to God, by ſuch a juſt and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Humiliation before his Divine Majeſty and Acknowledgment of our Humane Infirmity if never ſo little left to our ſelves, or but ſteping aſide out of the Order of his Holy Conduct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſubject themſelves intirely and readily to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Orders he hath appointed in his Church No ſober wiſe Man will expoſe himſelf, and lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others into Danger or Hazard, when he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without any Difficulty or Incumbrance put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and them into Safety and Security: No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will any ingenious Man, if he have committe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Miſtake, ſtand it out and maintain it againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Grave and Judicious Man: Much leſs will any conſiderate Man, who hath any ſenſe of God and regard to his tremendous Majeſty, dare t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſiſt in Oppoſing or Diſputing his <hi>Inſtitution</hi> or <hi>Orders:</hi> and therefore I ſhall here conclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I have received <hi>certain Queſtion</hi> concerning theſe Matters, but without an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Name of any who ſent them, or to whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould return <hi>Anſwer,</hi> though I ſhall forbear t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expoſe them, by making them publick; yet b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe I am debtor both to the wiſe and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unwiſe, for their Satisfaction, who are eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40207:27"/>moved with ſuch Scruples, or rely upon ſuch infirm Grounds, I ſhall return a brief compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Anſwer to the Eight Queſtions in theſe following Aſſertions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is the only <hi>Rule of Faith and Practice,</hi> rightly underſtood and uſed: But it is in many Caſes only a General Rule, leaving the ſpecial Application in ſome, to all Perſons; in others, to certain determinate Perſons. And therefore to require Expreſs and Plain Scripture for Faith and Practice in all things, doth proceed from Ignorance and Weakneſs in ſome, but too often from a diſingenuous Spirit of Contention, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt Deſign, or Satanical Deluſion.</p>
            <p>The Practices of the Primitive Chriſtians were ſome Permanent, to continue in the Church; others Temporary, and Alterable, according as there might be occaſion, for Order, Decency, and Edification, and did vary from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſeveral Churches and parts of the World; whereas the others were truly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, according to <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> his Rule, <hi>that is,</hi> univerſally obſerved without any known beginning ſince the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spirit of God</hi> was <hi>poured forth upon all Fleſh,</hi> when the Goſpel was Preached to all Fleſh, or to every Creature, <hi>that is,</hi> not only to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo. But as to individual Perſons, it was never ſo poured out
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40207:28"/>upon all Fleſh, but there were ſome things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquired; as <hi>Faith in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>ordinarily Baptiſm with Water, Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. Nor was <hi>the Manifeſtation thereof</hi> ever given to every one; but to every one to whom it was given, it was given to profit withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God:</hi> and, <hi>If any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.14, &amp; 9. But it is to be known and remembred, that a great and principal, and the moſt certain Leading of the Spirit of God is not ſenſible, or eaſily perceivable how it comes; but it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a Secret Illumination of the Mind to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Excellence of the things of God, and the Emptineſs and Deceitfulneſs of the things of the World; from which proceeds an Appetite to thoſe, and an Indifference to theſe; and in particular actions a like ſecret Illumination of the Mind, to apply the general Rules of the Scriptures to the particular Senſe, and an Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Will to what is ſo perceived to be the Will of God. And in more ſenſible Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Impreſſions, and Openings, as ſome call them, the <hi>Tryal</hi> is by their Agreement with what is agreed to proceed from the Spirit of God; <hi>that is,</hi> the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that is to be rejected, as coming from the Enemy: what is not inconſiſtent with that ought to be followed; or if doubtful, be referred
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40207:28"/>to the Judgment and Determination of the Elders, according to the Obſervations of the Ancients; or of the moſt Experienced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, eſpecially of ſuch as by their Office and Place are authorized, and obliged to be <hi>Guide of Souls.</hi> And thoſe who have preſumed to reject theſe Ordinary Means, which God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and eſtabliſhed in his Church, have frequently fallen into Miſchief.</p>
            <p>There are many of the Mind of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Act. 8.18. they are deſirous to purchaſe it, but not at the Price our Saviour ſet it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44, 46. And there are many falſe counterfeit Spirits, very officious to offer themſelves where they find hopes of Reception; and they always ſuggeſt and inſtigate to the following of their Leading, which is inſenſibly, and as they find their Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers diſpoſed, from the Holy Scriptures, and from Chriſt; and when they cannot prevail with them in that manner, they endeavour to fill them with Spiritual Pride and Conceitedneſs, make them admired by others, as extraordinary and very Holy Perſons, that they may make them think better of themſelves than they ought, and ſo get advantage of them that way. And there are generally two great Faults committed by moſt Pretenders to the Guidance of the Spirit. 1. They do not well conſider themſelves, and teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the neceſſary Qualifications pre-acquired for the obtaining of ſo great a Divine Favour.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40207:29"/>2. They neither conſider nor teach others the neceſſary Cautions and Directions for Tryal of Spirits. In general the Conſcientious Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Holy Scriptures, is a principal thing for both. For as the Law was our School-Maſter to bring us to Chriſt, ſo the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Obſervation of the externally revealed Will of God, which is Obedience, is our School-Maſter to prepare us for, and bring us to the true Spirit of God. But for more particular <hi>Cautions</hi> and <hi>Directions,</hi> that is a Subject too large for this Occaſion, and hath been largely treated of by others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queſtions</hi> concerning <hi>Baptiſm with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>the Eucharist or Holy Communion,</hi> are e'en ſuch as that of <hi>Naaman,</hi> 2 Kin. 5.11, 22. But they who make them are not like the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of that Heathen, who gave him this pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Admonition: <hi>If the Prophet had bid thee do ſome great thing, wouldſt thou not have done it? How much rather when he ſaith unto thee, Waſh and be clean?</hi> May they at leaſt take Example from that Heathen, who received the Admonition even from his Servants, even with the like bleſſed Succeſs. And this, with what I have ſaid before, is as much as I apprehend neceſſary to be ſaid to the <hi>Queſtions,</hi> for ſuch ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Perſons, as are willing to be ſatisfied and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the Truth: and I ſhall be ready to give them all further Satisfaction, when I underſtand where any real Scruple doth remain.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="review">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40207:29"/>
            <head>THE REVIEW.</head>
            <p>WHAT I have written, I have written with all Plainneſs and Simplicity, with all Candor and Impartiality, and Good Will to all; without any other Deſign than for the Service of God, and the Good of all; and without any Affection of any Ornament, as becomes the Majeſty of the Truths of God: Yet can I not expect but I muſt incurr the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of moſt in one thing or other, when I conſider the general Corruption of Mens Minds and Judgments, as well as of their Manners, at this time; not only of the Scandalous and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, or Hypocritical Profeſſors; but even of ſuch as are ſincere in many things, and deſervedly eſteemed in the World both for Parts and Honeſty; and yet in others, not ſo compleat as might be wiſhed, partly through the <hi>Byaſs of their own Diſpoſitions,</hi> and partly through the <hi>Common Cheat of Honourable Names;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Prudence, Moderation, Diſcretion, Charity,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40207:30"/>&amp;c. and their Contraries, calling Good, Evil; and Evil, Good; and partly through certain <hi>Falſe Notions,</hi> undermining the Integrity of the Evangelical Doctrine of Chriſt, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and rendring it of none Effect in many things; which have been <hi>introduced and recommended</hi> to the World, by <hi>a late Sect</hi> appearing in a very plauſible Form, but, in truth, generated by an unnatural Copulation of <hi>Church of England</hi> with ſome <hi>Socinian Principles,</hi> ſetting up their own <hi>Corrupt Humane Reaſon</hi> in the place of the <hi>Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and wreſting the divinely inſpired <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> to a Compliance with it; perſwading themſelves and others that the Noble Heroick Virtues, ſo much ſtudied and practiſed by the ancient Chriſtians, ſuch as <hi>Humility, Contempt of the World, Heavenly-mindedneſs,</hi> &amp;c. were for times of Perſecution; but we are under another Diſpenſation; as I my ſelf have been told by a Principal Author and Promoter of it; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging ſuch <hi>Temporizing Compliances,</hi> under the ſpecious Pretences of <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> as are not only Inlets to Sin, and Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances of Graces, but inconſiſtent with the Practices and Sentiments of the beſt Chriſtians of all Ages, with the Doctrines and Inſtructions of the Apoſtles, the Example and Precepts of our Saviour himſelf, (to ſay nothing of Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Counſels in this Age) our Baptiſmal
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40207:30"/>Engagements, and the Genuine Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and the Intereſt of the Kingdom of Chriſt in this World. What Gloſſes they make upon our Saviour's Sermon upon the Mount, I muſt leave to others better acquainted with them, to conſider. But, What can be expected from perſons ſo levened, but as ſevere Cenſures of this Writing as they take this to be of others? but that reaſonable Expreſſions of juſt Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Abuſes and Corruptions in Matters of Religion, or at abuſe of Scriptures to patronize Vanity, and by perſons profeſſing Religion, ſhould be cenſured for <hi>Paſſion?</hi> but that ſuch warm Expreſſions and Charges, as were neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to awaken ſuch out of a Deadly Slumber, as Experience had proved, could not be moved by gentler touches, ſhould be cenſured as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſs?</hi> and neceſſary plain Dealing with Mortals, for the Service of God, the Good of a Countrey, and the Salvation of Souls, be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as <hi>Indiſcretion, Diſreſpect to Superiors,</hi> and <hi>Saucineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to leave ſuch as are ready to <hi>wiſh,</hi> and to <hi>talk,</hi> but will <hi>do</hi> nothing but what may ſerve to recommend themſelves to thoſe whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations are moſt deſirable; are willing to uſe others, as the Cats foot, but will not touch the Work with one of their Fingers; nor inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the complement of a Dinner to conſult of what themſelves profeſs to be matter of great
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40207:31"/>Importance; whoſe Prudence prefers to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Religion with Perukes, and Laces, and Topknots, and Servants in Livery, rather than to bear the Reproach of Chriſt, in bearing Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt the Vanities of the Age, by the tacit Reproof of them in a decent but plain and a little unfaſhionable Attire; who preferr Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at home, in providing for the temporal concerns of themſelves and their Families, with ſome little creditable Acts of Charity, as we call it, before truſting to Providence in more liberal Contributions to unfaſhionable Good Works: to leave ſuch, I ſay, and to come cloſe to the buſineſs, to <hi>the State of the Church,</hi> (of which I am yet a Member, and am not ſatisfied to ſeparate while I live in the Nation, notwithſtanding all I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in it) for this is the Root of all, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to be conſidered; and they are to take care of the Diſſenters: If we conſider the Great things belonging to the <hi>Charge</hi> of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this Church, both <hi>ſeverally</hi> in their particular Dioceſſes, the State of the Clergy and People there; and <hi>joyntly</hi> to them all as one Body, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Court,</hi> and the <hi>Nobility;</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities;</hi> The <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſo far as Religion is concerned there; The <hi>Priſons,</hi> (which might be made Schools of Virtue, but are now Nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of all Vice and Wickedneſs) and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Perſons</hi> there; (for whoſe Aſſiſtance they of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion imploy the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40207:31"/>ableſt and beſt qualified of their Clergy, and we the moſt ordinary, though they are not a few, who are every Year Executed in this City, and throughout the Nation; The <hi>Foreign Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and the <hi>Propagation of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> by that Means abroad; for our Neglect of which the <hi>Monks,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſuch as we call <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> will riſe up in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them; and the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> at home; for they alſo belong to their Care, to remove all juſt Occaſions, give all reaſonable Satisfaction, and to uſe all truly Chriſtian Means to reduce them: If all theſe, beſides divers others, which cannot preſently be thought on, be conſidered, What Account can be given that may reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably paſs with a conſiderate Mortal Man, of any of theſe? and, What Account then can be given of all to the Immortal, All-ſeeing, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God.</p>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>Generals,</hi> of each of which a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and clear Account muſt be given by every one of that Order, what ſenſe he hath had of his Duty in that reſpect, and what Care and Endeavours he hath uſed in diſcharge thereof? To theſe I will add but one or two <hi>Particulars,</hi> of Occurrences in this Reign: One, of <hi>a Bill for Suppreſſion of Vice and Debauchery,</hi> drawn indeed at their Requeſt; but after it had been peruſed and perfected, not only by able Counſel, but by all the Judges then in Town, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40207:32"/>the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Polexfin,</hi> the Lord Chief Baron <hi>Atkyns,</hi> Mr. Juſtice <hi>Dolbin,</hi> Baron <hi>Letchmare,</hi> and I think one or two more, and fair written out put into their hands, and a Motion made by the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> to bring it into the Houſe, and granted by the Lords, and yet ſtifled and ſuppreſſed in their hands. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>a Needful and Hopeful Reformation,</hi> begun by the Authority and Encouragement of the QUEEN, and not only vigorouſly proſecuted here in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> but in a hopeful way in many other Cities and Counties all over the Nation, and this ſtopped firſt by a Combination of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex</hi> Juſtices, (I need ſay no more) but at laſt more effectually in a Judicature of Equity, in the Preſence of no leſs than ſeven of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelates, by two wicked Men, the one Speaker, and the other a Member of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Ralph Hartley, <hi>who is ſtill a Sufferer between a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of City Magiſtrates, and a Combination of</hi> Surry <hi>Juſtices, and ſome other perſons, and ſhamefully oppreſſed by them.</hi>
               </note> Juſtice of the Peace, who had been moſt diligent, and other perſons concerned in the Promotion of that Good Work, checked, vilified, and abuſed, without any juſt cauſe, to the diſcouragement of the Execution of the Laws, and Contempt of Her Majeſty's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and all in the Preſence of thoſe Biſhops, who came on purpoſe to countenance the Cauſe of Reformation, were ſatisfied of the Iniquity
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40207:32"/>of the Proceedings againſt it, and yet not one of them ever appeared after in it, to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe more than in one little printed Diſcourſe in Vindication of the Gentleman ſo abuſed, as aforeſaid. And what Account can be given of theſe things?</p>
            <p>It is a great Truth, <hi>That neither King, nor Parliament, nor Biſhops,</hi> of themſelves and their own Motion, <hi>have done any one Act,</hi> that I know of, <hi>worthy of the Name of Chriſtian.</hi> And where lyeth the Fault of all this, but at their door, who, inſtead of Admoniſhing, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing, and Animating to due Returns of true Gratitude in Fact to God, for his admirable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, have, by their Neglect, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it, provoked the Favours of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to withdraw, and to leave us to our ſelves, and to eat the Fruit of our own doings? And whence comes this Neglect of ſo many ſo obliged, but from a common Defect of Good Education at the Univerſities, and the Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Preferments?</p>
            <p>But is not this Great Uncharitableneſs, may our Grave Prudential Gentlemen ſay, thus to lay open to the World the Nakedneſs of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and of the Church? Doubtleſs as great as for a Phyſician to preſcribe a bitter Potion to a tender Patient; or a Chirurgeon to cut or burn, after tryal of more gentle means, what is found otherwiſe incurable. It is that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40207:33"/>they, at whoſe door lyeth the Root of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Evil, may give Glory to God, by taking Sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to themſelves, and giving Good Example <hi>Humiliation</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> to others. But they will not, I hope the deſpiſed <hi>Quakers</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſo wiſe, as to accept the Honour of beginni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Example. For <hi>all have ſinned, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort of the Glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Who call'd <hi>You</hi> to this Office? may o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prudentialiſts ſay: <hi>By what Authority doſt</hi> The <hi>this?</hi> and, <hi>Who gave</hi> Thee <hi>this Authority?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> who gave me Eyes to ſee, and a Heart to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſenſible of it, and a Mind to be Faithful to Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who call'd me and led me, by his Hand, to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Holy Service, not for filthy Lucre's ſake; n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to make a Trade of it; not to ſeek the Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Church; but to ſerve Him in the Servic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all Men, in the beſt manner I can.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
